<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The pearle found in England this is for the poor distressed, scattered ones in forraigne nations, from the royall seed of God, and heirs of salvation called Quakers, who are the Church of the living God, built up together of living stones in England, a visitation and uniting to the pearl of God which is hid in all the world that every one may turn into himself, and there feel it, and finde it / G.F.</title>
            <author>Fox, George, 1624-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 61KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40228</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10325466</idno>
  <idno type="VID">44856</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240951556</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1878</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R28004</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">10325466</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40228)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 44856)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1384:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The pearle found in England this is for the poor distressed, scattered ones in forraigne nations, from the royall seed of God, and heirs of salvation called Quakers, who are the Church of the living God, built up together of living stones in England, a visitation and uniting to the pearl of God which is hid in all the world that every one may turn into himself, and there feel it, and finde it / G.F.</title>
                  <author>Fox, George, 1624-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Simmons,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1658.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Society of Friends --  Pastoral letters and charges.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Inner Light.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:44856:1"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:44856:1"/>
                  <head>A Measuring-Rule CONCERNING LIBERTY AND PERSECUTION, AND Who have been the Persecutors, and who have been the Sufferers from the beginning.</head>
                  <head type="sub">
                     <hi>ALSO,</hi> The Stock and Line from whence the Persecutor hath had his rise and descent, and of what stock they are that cumber Gods Earth.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hristians should love one another, that is the Command of Christ, and is a mark by which they are known to be his Disciples. Secondly, they should love their very Enemies; and by this they differ from the <hi>Jews</hi> and Heathens, and all other people.</p>
                  <p>Now as for the late Act concerning the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God called <hi>Quakers,</hi> there is no penalty laid upon any
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:44856:2"/>man for the not breaking up of their Meetings, or not putting the Oath to them; therefore it will try and manifest what spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit men are of, and that which is in people wil be made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest now, because the Act is left to the Executor of it, without any penalty: Which Act had it been in the dayes of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles, would have taken hold upon Christ and his Apostles; for he had <hi>Twelve</hi> that often met together; and by this he might have but <hi>three,</hi> for if there were <hi>five,</hi> it had been in the trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gression; who also had seventy Disciples more. Now I say, if it had been in the days of Christ, it would have taken hold of him and his Disciples. Would Christ (and his Disciples) the Wisdom of God, do you think, have obeyed this Act, and not met with his Disciples? Or if the <hi>Jews</hi> should have made Laws to limit him but to four, do you think that Christ the Wisdom of God would have obeyed it, or his Disciples? And also Christ said to his Disciples, that they should wait together at <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> and not depart; and they did meet together, and you know that their meetings were different from the <hi>Jews</hi> and Heathen; and they were to wait together at <hi>Jerusalem</hi> until they received Power from on high, before they were to go to gather the Churches: And this was according to the Wisdom of God; Which if the <hi>Jews</hi> now had spoken to them that they should not meet, do you think the Disciples would have obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them, or the command of Christ? And when the Apostles had gathered Churches out of the <hi>Jews</hi> and the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and setled them, to whom they wrote their Epistles, and builded up one another in the holy Faith, and not to forsake the as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembling of themselves together: For if we sin wilfully after we have received the knowledge of the truth, then consider what is to be looked for: [80 now mark] if the <hi>Jews</hi> or the Heathen, out of whom the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> the <hi>Galatians,</hi> the <hi>Colossians,</hi> the <hi>Thessalonians</hi> and the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> were gathered into several Churches; if the Heathen and <hi>Jews</hi> had made Laws against them, that they should not meet saving four, do you think they would have obeyed it? Therefore consider of these things, and do as you would be done by, that is the Law and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets: Did not many suffer in the ten persecutions for meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing together, in the time about 650. years, before there was a Pope? And hath not many suffered for meeting together, by
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:44856:2"/>the <hi>Papists</hi> since; as look through the Book of Martyrs, how they suffered by the <hi>Papists,</hi> and called them <hi>Conventicles;</hi> and also in the time of the Martyrs sufferings in the ten Persecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and since the ten Persecutions, did they not make Laws they should not meet? And did they not call them <hi>Conventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles?</hi> And yet did they not meet in Barns or Houses, Woods and Fields? as you may read in the Book of Martyrs? Was these Martyrs disobedient in the ten Persecutions, and since to the Papists, in which so many thousands suffered for meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing together, for not paying Tythes, and for not swearing, and not yeilding to their principles and practice that persecuted them: Was it evil in them that persecuted them? And is it good now in you that make us to suffer for the same things? So are the Martyrs, and Persecutors, and you one, or the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryrs and we one, who have suffered all along? Whether they have not the nature of the Heathen that make to suffer, and not the nature of the Apostles? Likewise, have not many suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered here, as we now, for meeting together, and not swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, now in these dayes? As consider, in <hi>Oliver's</hi> dayes above three thousand suffered imprisonment, and some to death, who suffered for not swearing, and for Conscience-sake, as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Martyrs in the time of the ten Persecutions did, and by the Papists, and as we do now.</p>
                  <p>Therefore consider these things, for it is Christ Command that we do obey, and the Apostles Doctrine, which saith, <hi>Swear not at all:</hi> Consider now, Would not they in the ten Persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and the <hi>Papists,</hi> have punish'd Christ for preaching this Doctrine, and made him to suffer, (as we do now that own it) which saith, <hi>Swear not at all,</hi> but let your <hi>yea</hi> be <hi>yea,</hi> and your <hi>nay, nay,</hi> &amp;c. and the Apostles for holding it forth; for we do not these things in contempt or rebellion to any man; for our love and tenderness is, that all Magistrates and People would live in God's fear, and receive his Wisdom, by which all things were made and created, that by that they might be ordered to God's glory, and order that which God hath given them under their hands, to his honor, that to God they may be a blessing in their generation.</p>
                  <p>And consider, <hi>Daniel</hi> and the three children met, and diso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed the King's command; and <hi>Mordecai,</hi> who would not
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:44856:3"/>bow, disobeyed the Kings command; and the Midwives diso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed <hi>Pharoah</hi>'s command for not putting the Children to death: And the Woman who had seven sons which suffered by the Kings Law, because they would not eat Swines flesh, and one of her sons spake to his Mother, <hi>I will not obey the Kings command, I will obey the Law of Moses, which our fore-fathers obeyed.</hi> And <hi>Daniel</hi> disobeyed <hi>Darius</hi> his command, which was, that <hi>Daniel</hi> should not pray; and he prayed, and did not obey his command. And the Apostles disobeyed the High Priests and Counsels command, when they charged them that they should speak no more in that Name: Yet in the thing that is good, just and righteous, the righteous always have been, and are ever subject to every Ordinance of man for the Lord's sake, to such as were for the punishment of evil-doers, and for the praise of them that do well, that they might live a godly and peaceable life, [Mark] a peaceable life; for this cause they both prayed and paid tribute, not that they should bring them into an ungodly life, and an unpeaceable life, but that they should punish the evil-doers, that went into an ungodly life, and unpeaceable; for to that end were the higher Powers ordained over the ungodly, that went into the ungodly and unpeaceable life; for the ungodly are unpeaceable; and this is for the praise of them that do well: For the Law was made for transgressors, and not for the righteous. So they that be in the higher power, are to distinguish the precious from the vile; for not doing so, the Prophets often cryed against them; and when they turned against the righteous, peaceable and godly, then is the saying known which the Scripture speaks of, <hi>What shall separate us from the love of God? Shall Principalities, or Powers, or Thrones, or Dominions?</hi> Shewing, that there are Principalities and Powers that would separate from the love of God which they had in Christ Jesus, and that is from a godly and peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble life; and so there is a distinction, to be subject to that which punisheth the evil, and there is a suffering by that which would separate from the love of God: Now that which would separate, turns the Sword backwards against the righteous; and persecurors were alwayes blind, and could never see, but run upon their friends instead of their foes: And therefore these things consider and distinguish. God let <hi>Adam</hi> have liberty in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:44856:3"/>the earth, into which he was driven when he disobeyed his command; and God let <hi>Gain</hi> have liberty in the earth, after he had killed his Brother about Religion; and God let wild <hi>Ishmael</hi> have liberty in the Wilderness, after he was put out of <hi>Abrahams</hi> Family, the Father of the faithful, and the Serpent he had his liberty to feed upon the dust of the earth. Now I say, consider who are they who would not have Christ the just to live upon the earth; were not they them that Christ called Serpents, the <hi>Jews,</hi> the great professors? It was not Gods mind that people should be put out of the earth: God let <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> have liberty in the earth, after they had transgressed, though they were not to have liberty in the Garden. And <hi>Ish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mael,</hi> though he had not liberty in <hi>Abrahams</hi> Family, yet he had liberty in the Wilderness: And <hi>Cain,</hi> though he had not liberty in the presence of God, yet he had liberty to be a wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer in the Land of <hi>Nod.</hi> Therefore consider what mind that is that would not let men have liberty in the Earth, though he be not of your Assembly, yet he should have liberty in the Earth. Therefore consider whether that be the mind of God, or against it, yea or nay, though the Just comes over all these things, and are redeemed from the earth.</p>
                  <p>And if we must not meet together, how must we stir up one another, and Edifye one another, and provoke one another unto love and to good works, if we must not meet together to speak one to another. Consider this with understanding.</p>
                  <p>The world saith, <hi>Kiss the Book:</hi> The Book saith, <hi>Kiss the Son lest he be angry:</hi> And the Son saith, <hi>Swear not at all,</hi> but keep to <hi>yea</hi> and <hi>nay in all your communications; for whatsoever is more than this, comes of evil.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The World saith, <hi>Lay your hand on the Book;</hi> the Book saith, <hi>Handle the Word;</hi> and the Word saith, <hi>Handle not the traditions, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions, nor the rudiments of the world; and, This is my beloved Son, hear ye him, saith God,</hi> who is the L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fe, and the Truth, and the Light, and the Way to God, who saith, <hi>Swear not at all.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Therefore cumber not the ground you Adulterers, cumber not the earth you drunkards, cumber not the ground you swearers, cumber not the ground you proud, vain persons; cumber not the Earth you Earthworms, covetous persons; cumber not the ground you oppressors and exactors, and grin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:44856:4"/>of the poor, cumber not the ground; thou persecutor of the children of the Most High; cumber not the ground ye rich Gluttons; cumber not the earth you idle persons, that live in fulness of pleasures, and abundance of idleness, as the stalled Ox, so as he lieth in the mire and dirt; and as the full-fed horse, that must be breathed, with pleasures and sports, and your games of all sorts, and call it recreation for your idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness out of the service of the Lord; for thou who art so full, thou needest not work thy self down by pleasures, nor go to pleasures to get thee a stomach; if thou wilt wilt work it down with labour, work and chastity keeps all sweet, and labouring in the fear of the Lord,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cain</hi> the first birth, a persecutor; the first birth, a false wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipper; and <hi>Cain</hi> the first birth, that false worshipper, turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and turneth against <hi>Abel;</hi> and <hi>Cain</hi> the first birth, out of his stock came up the false-worshipper, who was the Inventer of <hi>Harps</hi> and <hi>Organs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Nimrods</hi> stock, false Worshippers, and out of <hi>Ham's</hi> stock he came, whose Spirit was not covered with truth, but with that which was from the truth; and so that spirit which runs from the truth, is not like <hi>Shem</hi> nor <hi>Japhet,</hi> and such worship not God in the spirit.</p>
                  <p>And they of the old World, that went from the Spirit of the Lord, and grieved his Spirit, they could not worship God in the Spirit.</p>
                  <p>And the <hi>Philistines</hi> grieved the Spirit of the Lord, and they were the persecutors, and they turned against the just.</p>
                  <p>And the <hi>Sodomites</hi> were the persecutors of the Just; and the <hi>Sodomites</hi> were such as lived in abundance of idleness and fulness; and those that were idle and full, persecuted the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous and the just, and the true Worshippers; and they that did, and do so, are the false Worshippers.</p>
                  <p>And <hi>Ishmael</hi> and his stock, the first birth, who scoffed at the just, and turneth against the just, a persecutor; and so are all wild men now.</p>
                  <p>And <hi>Esau</hi> the first birth, the prophane person, a false Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipper, a persecutor of <hi>Jacob;</hi> as many <hi>Esau's</hi> now, persecute them whom God loveth, who hate the first birth (being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secutors, prophane, false worshippers whom God loveth not.</p>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:44856:4"/>
                  <p>And the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> were, and are persecutors, and of the first birth.</p>
                  <p>And <hi>Balaam</hi> was a persecutor of the Just, and <hi>Balaam</hi> loved the Wages of unrighteousness; and such <hi>Balaams</hi> are now the lovers of the Wages of unrighteousness, and the persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors.</p>
                  <p>And the <hi>Jews</hi> that professed the Law, the Words of God, and did live out of the life of the Law of God; such did and do persecute the just; and such professors were always, and now are persecutors.</p>
                  <p>And alwayes such as preached for hire, and divined for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and taught for filthy lucre, and such Snepherds, Bishops and Priests that taught for the Fleece and the Wool, and for handfuls of Barley, and for pieces of bread, and were cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous; such were, and are persecutors and false Worshippers, and persecutors of the just, and the true Worshippers of God in the Spirit; and they that did so, grieved it.</p>
                  <p>And the Scribes, Pharisees and chief Priests, that had the Prophets and the Saints Words, and were not in the life of the Law and the Prophets, and Saints, and yet did profess their words, such did, and do persecute the Just, them that be in the life of the Saints.</p>
                  <p>And also, likewise all Christians that do profess the Prophets and Christ, and the Apostles, and <hi>Moses,</hi> and the Saints Words, and be out of their life and spirit, are the false Worshippers, and are the persecutors of the Just, and that is the end of all the profession without the life and the Spirit of God that the Saints dwell and walk in, who are the true Worshippers of God in the Spirit and Truth; and such as are led by the Spirit of God, they are the sons of God; and the false Worshippers are such as grieve the Spirit of God, and yet wil get the Saints words, and the sheeps cloathing, and not live in their life.</p>
                  <p>The first birth liveth in the Kingdom of the World, in <hi>strife,</hi> a <hi>Persecutor:</hi> The <hi>first birth</hi> is a <hi>Birth</hi> of <hi>strife,</hi> &amp; the second birth is heir of the Kingdom of the Lord; and the fruits of this birth is love, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Therefore come out of the first birth, to the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cain, Ham, Nimrod, Ishmael, Esau, Balaam, Sodomites, Philistins, Pharisees, Chief Priests, Babylon,</hi> were not these envious, wild,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:44856:5"/>prophane, idle, covetous, oppressors, persecutors, false wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shippers; and so you that be of the same nature, and of the same Birth, Was it not, and is it not the first birth? If it be so, know your own Kindred, and come out of this Kindred.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Scoffers, Scorners, Mockers, Reproachers, Revilers, Brawlers, Rail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, envious men,</hi> Do you profess God and Christ? These be all evil weeds, and cumbers God's ground. The <hi>Babylonites</hi> were, &amp; are persecutors of the Just, and the true Worshippers of God; and the <hi>Babylonites</hi> build up, and throw down, who be out of the standing Power, Life and Spirit of God, which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles and we are in; and so are not upon the Rock Christ Jesus, upon which we are, that changeth not.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>G. F.</signed>
                  </closer>
                  <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:44856:5"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:44856:6"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:44856:6"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THE</hi> PEARLE FOUND IN <hi>ENGLAND.</hi> This is for the poor distressed, scat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered ones in forraigne Nations.</p>
                  <p>From the Royall Seed of God and Heirs of Salvation, called <hi>Quakers,</hi> who are the Church of the Living God, built up together of living stones in <hi>England;</hi> A visitation and uniting to the <hi>Pearl</hi> of God which is hid in all the World, that every one may turn into himself, and there feel it and finde it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>G. F.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Simmons,</hi> at the <hi>Bull</hi> and <hi>Mouth</hi> neer <hi>Aldersgate,</hi> 1658.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:44856:7"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:44856:7"/>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>FRIENDS,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THE <hi>Pearl</hi> is hid in the field, and the field is the World, and the World is in your hearts, and there you must dig deep to find it, and when you have digged deep &amp; found it, you must sell all to purchase and redeem this field, and there you shall know the Merchants man that makes the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change, and there shall you know Christ <hi>in you the hope of glory,</hi> to save you, and redeem you, <hi>the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manuel, God with us;</hi> and there shall you know the Woman that lost the piece of silver, and was seeking it without; but when the candle was lighted, and the house swept, she found it in her own house, and then she did know the joy, and went and told her neighbours; and then she did know the day-star rise in her heart, and the day dawning whereby the light shal be known, that shines from the East to the West, and the word of faith <hi>in the mouth and heart,</hi> &amp; the oyl is in thy Lamp if thou enter in with the Bridegroom; the light shines in thine own heart to give thee the light of <hi>the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Glory of God in the face of Jesus Christ,</hi> from whence it comes, and the anointing which abideth in thee will teach thee, and as it doth teach thee thou shalt continue <hi>in the Father and the Son,</hi> from whence this holy Ʋnction comes, and hast received it, and here thou shalt know <hi>that thou need no man to teach thee, but as the same anointing doth teach thee,</hi> and the ingrafted word, able to save your souls, is in your hearts, and <hi>the hidden man of the heart,</hi> which is renewed day by day is found there, and the
<pb facs="tcp:44856:8"/>meek and quiet spirit, which is with the Lord of great price, is found in thee, and the Covenant of grace that brings salvation is in thy heart, and in thy mouth, to season it and thy words, and to teach thee <hi>to deny all ungodlinesse and worldly lusts,</hi> and the heap of Teachers set up by mens lusts in the World, that turn this grace into wantonnesse, and lives wildely, and it will teach thee to live soberly.</p>
                  <p>The Devil went from the truth, and deceived the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and abode not in it, and he rules in all the hearts of the children of disobedience, that obeys not the truth, he that went out of the truth, and so they become Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues of Sathan, and so murderers. <hi>Cain</hi> went from the truth, the <hi>Jews</hi> went from the truth, and so of the Devil the false prophets, Antichrists, inwardly ravened from the truth, and so all these turned against the just, murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, &amp; so who is come to the just that they ravened from, over all these they reign, and brings people to God, to reign over all this thats out of the truth, and contrary to it.</p>
                  <p>All you high gazing Professors and hypocrites. <hi>The Kingdom of heaven is within you (like unto a grain of mustard-seed, like unto leaven)</hi> that comes not by observations, who are and have been gazing for it without you.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:44856:8"/>
                  <head>The Pearl found in <hi>ENGLAND.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ome all ye wearied Souls who have been long travelling these many yeares since the dayes of Apostacy from the true Apostles and Disciples, where darknesse and mists has gone over the earth, and blinded and darkened the minds and eyes of the people, the true Ministry being lost since the dayes of Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stacy, whereby people has run into heads and parties and sects, and truth amongst them held in the unrighteousnesse, the sin and the enemity in every ones mind, men slaying one another about Religion and for Religion, and about worship which was not the work of the true Christians, true Ministers and true Apostles, but they brought people into unity and wrestled against principalities and powers and spiritual wickednesses, which ruled in the children of disobedience, and brought them to the thing which they disobyed, so the enemity having been in all minds of professors upon earth, amongst Christians, Teachers, people and Rulers, who would slay one another, murther one another about worship, about Scriptures, the Prophets, Christs and the Apostles words; here is the Devil, the old adversary of man, got amongst professors, provoking to destroy one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, keeping up the form of the Saints words, in the nature of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> that kept up the form of the Prophets and <hi>Moses</hi> words, which Christ said <hi>were of their Father the Devil,</hi> amongst whom the <hi>Pearl</hi> was lost, as has been lost since the dayes of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postacy from the Apostles life, Christs life; Nations covered with ignorance like unto waters; Now the Prophets, Christs and the Apostles they were in unity in the Spirit which led them to speak forth the Scriptures, wch now being professed amongst Christians in Christendome, but the life of Christ, of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and the Apostles, they having been out of, they want the bond of peace, the unity; for the unity is in the Spirit which is <hi>the bond of peace,</hi> which Christ, the Prophets and Apostles were in that gave forth the Scriptures, so words, forms, traditions,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:44856:9"/>inventions, idols, have people fallen out one with another about; But now that is manifest which comprehends the world, which was before the world was made; <hi>Christ Jesus the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of God, which doth enlighten every man that comes into the world,</hi> that all through the light might believe and feel the witness in themselves, in which people come to have peace with God, and every one receiving the light, that they be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightened withall; him they receive that hath enlightened them, <hi>Christ Jesus</hi> in their own particulars, which gives them to see their sins, and so to see the Saviour of their Souls, and to know the Saviour of their Souls, <hi>Christ Jesus</hi> from whence the light comes; for saith God <hi>Ile give him for a Covenant, a light to the Gentiles, and a Leader to the people, and Ile make a new Covenant with the house of</hi> Israel <hi>and</hi> Judah, them that had the old, <hi>Ile put my Laws in their minds, Ile write them in their hearts, and they shall not need to say know the Lord,</hi> which thousands in <hi>England</hi> do witnesse this covenant, <hi>that they need not say know the Lord,</hi> in which they have <hi>unity one with another, and peace with God through Christ Jesus</hi> his covenant and witnesses the power, and feels the Covenant of light, the Leader, and Gods covenant fulfilled, him that <hi>Abraham, David,</hi> the prophets gave testimony of should come, him that the Apostles did give testimony of was come and risen, he is enjoyed, in which people comes to have unity one with another, and the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and the thing the Scriptures speak of, &amp; God; And in the light him by whom the world was made, there is no occasion of stumbling, so the covenant of light that God said he would give by his prophets for a Leader of the people, the way to the Father, thousands witnesse him leading of them out of the first <hi>Adam</hi> drove from the father, who is the end of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and he is leading of them up to God and is their Teacher, and they have found him in them and come to him and found rest for their Souls, and their Souls hast rest, and they have taken in <hi>Christs yoke</hi> that is <hi>easy,</hi> and his <hi>burthen</hi> that is <hi>light,</hi> and he is become their Teacher; And mens yokes, and burthens, and teachings, and doctrines comes to be ceased from, and cast off, which have ruled since the dayes of the Apostacy from the Apostles, and the <hi>Pearl</hi> that hath been hid in the Earth is found,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:44856:9"/>and the Morning-star is risen, and the day is dawned, and the true light shines and wisedome, (which, all the knowledge, understanding and wisedome that man cannot comprehend nor find) cryes in the streets to the simple ones, and for all to fear God that they may receive it, the wisedome of God Christ Jesus, him by whom the world was made, the wisdome by which all things were made and created, and to come out of sin and transgression which all the world has lived in that have the form of godlinesse, but have been in the transgression from the life, and ravined from it, and have been in the sheeps cloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but every where has been ready to worry the Lambs, them that has gotten their cloathing, the outside, the form of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linesse, but inwardly ravined from the life, which Christ said should come, <hi>John</hi> saw was come, which all the world hath been after, so there has been the <hi>Pearl</hi> hid, and the life of Christ the Prophets and Apostles has been lost, and the form they have had, but life and glory is risen that manifests and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers all things, and Churches and Teachers that has not been made by the will of God, which has got up since the dayes of the Apostles, from all such is God bringing his people to teach them himselfe, and from all their wayes to Christ the way to the Father, and from all their Churches to the Church in God, the pillar and ground of truth, and over them, and to the anointing which abideth within, to which people are come, which as it doth teach them, <hi>they continue in the Son of God and the Father, and need not that any man teach them, but as the same anointing doth teach them, wch abideth in them,</hi> and as it <hi>doth teach them, they continue in the Son of God,</hi> in the wisdom of God, they continue in the life and in the truth; they continue in the covenant of God; they continue in the power of God, and the Rock Christ Jesus, him by whom the world was made, before it was made; in which comes people to have peace with God, and one with another, and the foundation of many gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations is found and witnessed, that breaks down the bond of Iniquity that made the breach betwixt God and man, which makes up the breach betwixt God and man, whereby health and glory &amp; peace in the rereward is felt, the election is known before the world was made, which hath obtained the promise
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:44856:10"/>of eternal life, and the power of an endlesse life is enjoyed, and the world to come. Therefore come all hither ye scattered ones over the world, the power of God in you feel, &amp; then you feel <hi>Christ Jesus who hath enlightened every one that comes into the world,</hi> then you will feel <hi>the covenant,</hi> wch you have with God, <hi>wch will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lot out your sin and transgression,</hi> then you will feel <hi>the blood of Christ Iesus which cleanseth from all sin, which light discovers</hi> as you walk in the light, as he is in the light, and you will have fellowship one with another; The Kingdom of Heaven is seen, <hi>which is as a grain of musterd seed which is within,</hi> and many have received it, and are become as little children, and them that be conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into the Kingdom, they bring forth their things new and their things old; and many are digging in the field, which is the world, which is set in their hearts seeking for the <hi>Pearl,</hi> and many have found it, and many merchant-men be exchanging, <hi>glory to the Lord for ever;</hi> so the <hi>Pearl is within you,</hi> that is found in the Nation of <hi>England,</hi> and all people upon the Earth come in to your selves, find the <hi>Pearle</hi> in you, the precious <hi>Pearl</hi> there has layen under the earth, and come out of your talk and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession in words, in which the <hi>Jews</hi> were, in whom the <hi>Pearle</hi> was hid, that you may find the <hi>Pearle</hi> in your selves, and the kingdom there <hi>within you,</hi> though it be <hi>like a grain of mustard seed,</hi> its like unto <hi>leaven,</hi> it will leaven you up into <hi>a new Lump;</hi> Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, Churches, Notions without life shall wither, fade like flowers, wither like grasse, be burnt up like stubble, sticks and chaffe that has cumbered the ground, the wheat is got out into the Garner, the Lambs are leaping, the Father carries them in his hands, the babes born of the immortal seed by the word of God, and are at the breast sucking, living riches is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fested, God the Father is known and is worshipped in the spirit and in the truth, in that which the Devil is out of, the blood of Jesus is witnessed, which flows and cleanseth from all sin, the fountain is opened where is the washing of all sores, and God is bringing people into the life that gave forth the Scriptures, that the Prophets, Christ and the Apostles were in, in which life they shall see their words and have unity with them, and with the Lord God, and one with another, and the word of faith is possessed and known in the heart, in the mouth, that
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:44856:10"/>divides asunder the precious thoughts from the vile thoughts, &amp; precious desires from vile desires, &amp; precious affections from vile affections, &amp; it is in the mouth to divide asunder the precious words from the corrupt words, and this word that divides asunder <hi>the precious from the vile</hi> is quick and powerful, and sharper then a two edged sword, for vile seperated from God, the word that divides it, the vile from the precious hammers it down, burns it up, cuts it down, reconciles to the father, and separates thatvvch seperated; so the word of God in you all feel, in all your occasions, and then you will have the word of wisdom, that will divide asunder your precious thoughts from your vile thoughts, your precious words from your vile words, and this will teach you in all your occasions; The <hi>Pearle</hi> in you come to know, the seed in you come to know, which seed is Christ that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herits the promise, which now is risen in thousands, who are come to be Heires of the promise, and Heirs of God, and Heirs of the world that has no end; The <hi>anointing in you</hi> all come to know which abideth in you, and then <hi>you need not that any man teach you, but as the same anointing doth teach you,</hi> and as it doth teach you, you shall <hi>continue in the Son of God</hi> from whence it comes, in him <hi>by whom the world was made, before it was made.</hi> The Kingdom of Heaven in you all come to know, which is like but <hi>a grain of mustard seed,</hi> and you all come to receive it, you will all come to be as little children, and there you will come to feel the leaven, which leavens you up into a new Lump, and so to know the Kingdome of the world, to become the Kingdome of the Son of God, and this is the Kingdom of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven like <hi>a grain of mustard seed in you,</hi> which never consented to sin, and receiving that, you come to be as little children, and to know the leaven that will leaven you up into a new Lump; which thousands do witness in <hi>England;</hi> And the light all come to know which shines in your Hearts, which must give you <hi>the light of the knowledge of the glory of God in the face of Christ Jesus,</hi> in Christs face from whence the light comes, him by whom the world was made, glorified with the Father before the world began; <hi>I am the Light of the World, and do enlighten every one that comes into the World,</hi> saith Christ the second <hi>Adam,</hi> who is
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:44856:11"/>the way again to God, man being drove from God in the first <hi>Adam,</hi> Christ the second <hi>Adam, the Life, the Truth, the Way</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to God, which every one that comes into the world is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightened withall; or man being drove from God, he is drove from Life, and drove from God, he is drove from Truth, and drove from God, he is drove from his wisdome, and drove from God, he is drove from his Righteousnesse, and from his power, under the power of Sathan; so Christ the power of God through death destroyes death, and him that hath the power of death, the Devil, and is over it before the world was made, the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer of man kind out of the fall, <hi>who doth enlighten every man that comes into the world, that all through him might believe,</hi> and he that is come into the light with wch he is enlightened with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, he is come into the wisdome of God, into the righteousness of God, he is come into the way, he is come to Christ the power of God, to the Rock, him by whom the world was made, and so come to the life and rest and peace; he that believes is saved, he that doth not is condemned, <hi>and he that believeth hath the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness in himself, and hath set to his seale, that God is true,</hi> who hath per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed his promise, and sees the Prince of this world is judged, and is come into the Righteousnesse of God, Christ Jesus, so Christ Jesus he is the Righteousnesse of God, he is the new and living vvay and the one way to the Father, and all the many wayes be in the first <hi>Adam,</hi> drove from God, in the transgressi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Christ the second <hi>Adam</hi> the Lord from Heaven, as death came by the one, life came by the other, and as darknesse came by the one, light comes by the other, who is the Right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eousnesse of God, the Truth, the Life, as unrighteousnesse by the one, Righteousnesse by the other, as untruth by the one, so Truth by the other, as the many wayes from the Father by one, so the one way to the Father by the other; there is disobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience by one which brings death, there is obedience by the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which brings life; him you must all come to find <hi>in you, Christ Jesus except you be reprobates,</hi> then you come to witnesse the substance, then you come to know the everlasting Covenant, then you come to know the Prince of peace, the Prince of life and comfort of what you do professe in your own particulars,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:44856:11"/>in coming into the Covenant of the Father; <hi>Death has reigned from Adam till Moses, and the Law and the Prophets were untill John, Moses</hi> had the Law which went over all transgression, and answered that in all people wch was transgressed; <hi>Moses</hi> words people has had, but they have been out of the life of <hi>Moses,</hi> the Prophets words they have had, but they have been out of the life of the Prophets; <hi>Johns</hi> words they have had, but have been out of the life of <hi>John;</hi> Christs words they have had, but the life of Christ they have been out of the Apostles words they have had, but the life of the Apostles they have been out of; the Apostates since the dayes of the Apostles; Now Christ said in the 7. and 24. of <hi>Mathew, that false Prophets and Antichrists should come,</hi> to his Diciples before he was offered up, and Christ gave to his disciples the marks by which they should know them, <hi>that they should be inwardly ravening,</hi> that is, devourers, <hi>having sheep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> cloathing,</hi> that is the outside, <hi>but Wolves, do men gather grapes of thorns or figs of thistles? by their fruits you shall know them;</hi> Now before the Disciples decease which Christ said unto them false Prophets and Antichrists should come, they saw they were come already into the world, as saith 1 <hi>John,</hi> 2. and 4. <hi>little chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren I write unto you that it is the last time, whereof you have heard, say Antichrist should come,</hi> whereby you know it is the last time, for there are many Antichrists, many false Prophets already in the world, <hi>and they went forth from us that it might be manifest, they were not of us, for had they been of us, no doubt they would have continued with us;</hi> but saith he, <hi>ye have an anointing which abideth in you,</hi> to the Saints, <hi>and ye need not that any man teach you, but as the same anointing doth teach you,</hi> and as it doth teach you, <hi>ye shall continue in the Son of God and the Father;</hi> and Christ who said they should come, he bad them not go after them, the false Prophets and Antichrist which should be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly raveners; <hi>John</hi> saw they were come; he told the Saints the anointing was in them to teach them, and the false Prophets and Antichrists of which they had heard say should come, they were already in the world, and went out from them, and were inwardly Raveners, <hi>which all that dwelt upon the earth went after, and all the world came to worship the Beast and false Prophets, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:44856:12"/>all Nations drunk of the wine of her fornications, Rev.</hi> 13. <hi>and</hi> 17, 18. And now cryes the professors and Teachers of the world, they are come but now, and now is the last time; but <hi>John</hi> did not say, it was the last time when all Nations had drunk the Cup of fornication, and all that dwelt upon the Earth had wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipped the beast; Now we say people are coming from the false Prophets, those which Christ said should come, <hi>John</hi> saw was come wch went forth from them, <hi>wch all people that dwelt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the earth went after, and all Nations came to drink the cup of her fornications, and she sits upon the waters, and the waters are peoples, and Nations, and Tongues, and Languages and multitudes, Rev.</hi> 17. where she sits, tongues are waters, peoples waters, languages wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Nations waters, multitudes waters, for they have been from the Rock, they which Christ said should come, and <hi>John</hi> saw was come that went forth from them; and so have been as waters, and so <hi>the first beast out of the Sea, and the second out of the earth;</hi> And all this <hi>Babylon</hi> building up and throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down, and all these crosses and Images, pictures, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipping of Names and Idols, and all these pulpits, Priests, Tythes, Churches with Crosses in the Church-yards and Church ends has been of them, and all this making of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters by the will of men, by their Schooles and Colledges for covetous ends, &amp; covetous practices are amongst the Apostates, which are apostatized from Christs Disciples, who went forth freely, sent forth by him &amp; all these names amongst people cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Christians are of the Beast, and given by the beast since the dayes of the Apostles in the apostacy; in their dayes there was not so many Names given to Christians; so that which Christ said should come, <hi>John</hi> saw was come, which went forth from them <hi>which all the world went after and worshipped the beast and false Prophets, but who had their Names written in the Lambs Book of life</hi> before the foundation of the world, <hi>which kept the testimony of Jesus,</hi> against whom <hi>the beast and false Prophets should make war, and should overcome, and the Woman fled into the Wildernesse, and the man-child was caught up unto God,</hi> that which ravined forth, which was the Wolf from the life, turned
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:44856:12"/>against them that kept the life; the testimony of Jesus which is the Spirit, but now the Lamb and the Saints have the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, for every one that comes into the World being enlightened, they which go from the light which they be enlightened with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all they inwardly ravine, and you may see these were not those called Heathens that got the sheeps cloathing, that went forth from the Apostles which had been amongst them, but did not continue ravined from the life, had the sheeps cloathing, kept the outside, but made war against those that kept the life, that kept the Spirit the testimony of Jesus and killed them; here began the apostacy; amongst these has come up all this trash, when they ravined from the life, stood not in the councel of God, but made Ministers by their own wills, and apostatized from the true Crosse the power of God, and from the true Church, <hi>the Pillar and ground of Truth,</hi> and from the true Apostles, and set up a Church with a crosse on the end of it, and these are they that have brought up all these pulpits, Tythes, Temples, Saboths, Schools, Colledges, <hi>and these are they that despise prophesy and quench the Spirit,</hi> and limits the holy one which sets them in confusion; the order and practise of the Church of the Apostles <hi>is; if any thing be revealed to one that sits by, let the first hold his peace, for you may all speak one by one, that all may learne, and all may be comforted;</hi> so from all these Apostates and apostasy, the beast and the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of his names, and his heads, and horns, and crowns, and his languages, and his crosses, and his Churches, pulpits, and his Teachers made by the will of man, is God bringing his people, and the Lamb and the Saints has the Victory, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for ever to the highest, and the everlasting Gospel shall be preached to them that dwell upon the earth, for all that dwell upon the earth have worshipped the beast, and gone after them that inwardly ravined, that Christ said should come, <hi>John</hi> saw was come, that went out from them, and so all Nations has been like a Wildernesse, that bryers and thornes and thistles may be gathered of them, and in this may every one see his fruits; but who had their Names written in the Lambs book of life, and kept the testimony of Jesus; for all Nations
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:44856:13"/>have drunk of the cup of her fornications, and this was that, that made war with the Saints and overcome them, but now the Lamb and the Saints have got the Victory over that wch Christ said should come, <hi>John</hi> saw was come, which all the world went after, and now he is redeeming the pure Miste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; now shall the Saints and the holy Peophets rejoyce over her, who are come to that which she went from, now shall the holy Tabernacle be witnessed with man; now shall the holy City be witnessed, and the heavenly <hi>Jerusalem, now cryes the Spirit come, and him that heares bids come, and the bride saith come, for the Lamb and the Saints has Victory, and now is the marriage of the Lamb, and to every one that thirsteth he will give of the water of life freely;</hi> so every one that comes into the world being enlightened, having a light from the Lamb, being turned to the light, that Christ Jesus the Lamb of God hath enlightened them withall, and believing in the light which will let you see your sins, with it you will see <hi>the Lamb of God which takes away sins;</hi> for all these Tythes, and pulpits, and Temples, and Priests are come up since the dayes of the Apostles amongst them that apostatized from them, for the true Apostles witnessed against the true Temple which <hi>Solomon</hi> built, and said <hi>their bodies were the Temples of God,</hi> and the Apostles witnessed against the true Priest-hood whose lips were to preserve the peoples knowledge, and offered for his own sins and the sins of the people, and witnessed the everlas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Priesthood and the one offering, and Christ the treasure of wisdome and knowledge, which doth enlighten every man that comes into the World, and said the light that shined in their hearts wch came from him would give them the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the glory of God in the face of Christ Jesus, and with that light they saw the glory which was with the Father be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the world began, from whom the light comes, him by whom the world was made; And the Apostles brought them off the true Tythes, and said <hi>the Priesthood was changed, and the Law was changed also, and Commandement disanulled</hi> wch gave them Tythes, and Christ Jesus was come the Son of God, the end of all similitudes and likenesses, as <hi>Hebr.</hi> 7. So as
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:44856:13"/>was said before, these Priests, Tythes, Temples, pulpits were made by the will of man since the dayes of the Apostles in the apostacy, and these Churches amongst whom are all these Names and several worships, and opinions, and judgements, and having the sheeps cloathing, but every one as a Wolf ravined from the life, and ready to devour one another, so the form of godlinesse has been long amongst people, but the life and power has been wanting, which they were in, that gave forth the Scriptures in wch people have unity, from it they have been apostatized; the worship of God in Spirit and truth has been wanting, from this they have been apostatized, in wch spirit they gave forth the Scriptures wch is the bond of peace, in it is the unity, &amp; the worship of the father in the truth, in that wch the Devill is out of, in wch is no enmity, and so all having been inwardly Raveners that have been from the life within, they have been Wolves in sheeps cloathing rave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning one after another to devour one another, and their fruits has been bryers and thornes so profession of Religion has been amongst people, but the life has been wanting, into wch life God is now bringing his people to that wch they all ravined from, with wch they shall see all the Apostates in the Apostacy, and fathom over the Heads of them all, with vvhich they shall come to see the rock Christ Jesus the Covenant of light and life and peace; so that which may be known of God is manifest within people wch God hath shewed unto them, that when they do the things that are not convenient, not right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eous or worthy of death, with that of God in them all they can tell, and to that of God in them all they must come, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they do hold the Truth in the Righteousnesse, or retain God in their knowledge, or retain his covenant of light in which is the peace with God and one with another; for the <hi>Jews</hi> they held truth, the Prophets, and <hi>Moses,</hi> and the Saints Words, but their minds being reprobated from that which might be known of God made manifest in them, wch God had shewed unto them, they held it in the unrighteousnesse in the sin and enemity, so that was that age; now the ages since, people has held truth, Christs words, the Prophets words,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:44856:14"/>Apostles words, but it has been in the unrighteousness that is in the sin, in the Enemity in every ones mind, and so there is the adversary and the wicked one amongst people, professors and Christians that has that name, and so they become Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogues of Sathan, in enmity one against another, giving one another names, gathering together in Sects one against another, cages of unclean Spirits, habitations of Dragons, yet truth held, in the unrighteousness in the enmity which makes them to slay one another about it; and so there is the Devil puts men on to kill one another about Religion, wrastle against flesh and blood, and the while the power of darkness, &amp; spiritual wickedness rules, but those are no true Christians, no Ministers of Christ that do so, but they are all from that which may be known of God made manifest in them, wch God hath shewed to them as the <hi>Jews</hi> was, outward <hi>Jews,</hi> not inward, outward Christians, not inward; for he is a true Christian that hath Christ in him, as he was a true <hi>Jewe</hi> who was one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, so to that which may be known of God manifest in them must all people be brought before they retain God in their knowledge, from whence it comes, or retain his Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant Christ Jesus the end of the Prophets <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> whom the Apostles preached, before the world was made, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was made, in which you come to have peace with God, in whom truth must be held, and spoken as it is in Jesus, and then it is held in Righteousnesse and spoken in peace, the seed of God being brought forth, and the covenant of light and life witnessed, the Lamb being risen which makes the powers of the earth to rage that be out of the fear of God, and Christ Jesus is come to reigne, the same yesterday, to day, and for ever, which makes all the Ministers, Teachers, Prophets, &amp; Antichrist to rage that have been made by the will of man, and Schooles, and Colledges, that speaks a divination of their owne brain, and not from the month of the Lord, and all Ministers, Teachers, Prophets, Pastors, Shepherds, Guides, and Leaders of the people that has gotten Christs, the prophets, Apostles words, &amp; professors of them, being found out of the life of the prophets, Christ and the Apostles with the life of Christ,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:44856:14"/>of the prophets and Apostles are they all judged wch makes them rage, wch life is now made manifest, glory to the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est for ever, and the Lord is come to teach his people him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self by his Spirit, and to gather them from all the worlds wayes, Teachers, to himselfe, and so all upon the earth wch professe Christs words, the prophets and Apostles, they are ragnig against their life, wch is now manifest, and be raging against Christ which is now manifest in his Saints, Christ the same to day, yesterday and for ever, so the seed of God is risen, glory to the Highest for ever, which seed is Christ in the Male and in the female, whereby many males and females are come to confesse Christ the seed, in them which is Christ who has the promise; and so are become Heires of the promise, Heires of God, Heires of life, and Heires of the world that has no end, and the Rulers of the Earth takes Councel toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther against the Lord, and against his anointed, and his babes as you may read, and as they may read, that now are taking councel against him where the anointing is manifest, such are they that slayes him in the particular, and are the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders that reject the Corner-stone, but the stone that is cut out of the mountains without hands shall dash the Head of gold to pieces, and the breast of silver the King of <hi>Babylon,</hi> who have an ear they may heare; And so the world is crying out for their honour, and crying out for their bendings and bowings and doffing their hats, and cryes <hi>Jacob</hi> bowed to <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sau,</hi> it seemes that <hi>Esau</hi> is Lord among you yet, &amp; not servant, its granted there was a time, that <hi>Daniel</hi> bowed to <hi>Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezzar,</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> bowed to <hi>Pharaoh</hi> its granted, and there was a time that <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his host was in the Sea, the Family of <hi>Jacob</hi> rejoycing over them; there was a time that <hi>Esau</hi> must be as stubble, and <hi>Jacob</hi> ride over the high places of the Earth, and <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> brought down amongst the beasts to eat grasse like an Oxe, until he knew that the most high did rule in the Kingdoms of men, and the elder must serve the younger; he that hath an ear let him heare, and as for the hat, its honour amongst men, honour below, and not honour above, while people are seeking for this honour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:44856:15"/>they lose the honour which is above which Christ com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands to seek, and questioned them that were there receiving honour one of another, and seeking honour of men, how could they believe, and said moreover I receive not honour of men, <hi>I which am the Light of the World,</hi> him by whom the World was made, which enlightens every man that comes into the World, and does not come amongst the Sons of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> drove from God to receive their honour, but to spoil it, deface it, stain their pride, deface their honour, mar their glory, stain their beauty; so the light which every man that comes into the World is enlightened withall, the light in him which hath enlightened him will not receive the honour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, but will condemne him if he receives it, and that is it which brings to seek honour from above, and stain the glory that is below; so the first <hi>Adam</hi> in the transgression receives honour of the Earth, but the second <hi>Adam</hi> receives it not, nor will the light in them receive it, which comes from the second <hi>Adam,</hi> so I have a witnesse in all mens consciences up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the earth, that will not receive honour of men below, but of God, and that comes from above.</p>
                  <p>And the Teachers of the World, and Ministers, and Pastors, and Doctors, and Shepherds has told us that the Hebrew, Greek and Latine was the original, and they were the ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox Ministers to open the Scriptures to us, and they had the original, when as <hi>Moses</hi> said that all the earth was of one language before <hi>Babel,</hi> &amp; <hi>Nimrod</hi> the mighty hunter whose stock was of <hi>Ham,</hi> whom God did confound into the many lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, he was the beginning of the building of <hi>Babel;</hi> and <hi>Moses</hi> said like unto me will God raise up a Prophet, him shall you heare, and when this Prophet was come, Christ Jesus they crucified him, and when they crucified him, they write a superscription over him in Letters of Hebrew, Greek and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine; now here stands the Worlds Original over Christ, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the life when they crucified him; the beginning of these many languages was <hi>Babel;</hi> and <hi>Pilate</hi> he could not open the Scriptures with Hebrew, Greek and Latine, but crucified Christ who is the substance of the Scriptures, and when he
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:44856:15"/>had done, he set his many languages on the top of him; and said <hi>John</hi> in the <hi>Revelations,</hi> they must be redeemed out of languages, which they have told us was the Original, that which was set a top of Christ when he was crucified, a top of the life, but now the life is risen, Christ is risen, who had the many languages a top of him, Orthodox men a top of him, Christ is risen that fathomes <hi>Babel</hi> and <hi>Babylon</hi> before <hi>Babel</hi> or <hi>Babylon</hi> was, who had the many languages a top of him, which is the Worlds Original, so the life is risen a top of it, which they set a top of him and over them, and saith it is the Original, and say they must open the Scriptures with it, with wch they run all into confusion <hi>Babylon,</hi> so betwixt <hi>Babel</hi> and <hi>Babylon</hi> they may walk and see by plain Scriptures how the many languages were set over Christ; and <hi>Pilate</hi> could not open the Scriptures with them, nor can they now open the Scriptures with their many languages, but breaks into heaps, heads and parties, for if they could open, they would satisfy one another, and come all into one, for that which gave forth is one, which must open them again; So all people, Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Professors be all upon heaps in confusion about the words of the Scriptures, saying that is the Original, and they are stopped at <hi>Babel,</hi> for all the earth was of one language before, and they stood on the top of Christ, and the call is out of many languages, out of <hi>Babylon, Babylon</hi> is the end of them, and the life is risen that staines their pride, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faceth their glory, and marres their beauty, for they have a pride, a glory, a beauty in their languages, which they call the Original, the naturals, and the light lets see before <hi>Babel</hi> or <hi>Babylon</hi> was, or <hi>Pilate</hi> either, in the beginning the Covenant of light with God, and when that people did Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine to build <hi>Babel,</hi> they went out of the life, which God confounded into the many languages, that they might not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scattered, and God scattered them as he will all other ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therings, that are gathered with Imaginations of him, and are the builders, and goes from the life of God within them, and so from God, and they that crucified Christ they were from
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:44856:16"/>the life, and they set the many languages a top of Christ which was the life, and they that were <hi>Babylon,</hi> were them that ravined from the Spirit of God in them, and went from the Apostles Doctrine into the many languages which the redemption is from, and so they cannot endure to heare talke of the life, and the Spirit of God within, and the light; and these are they that set up languages; but now the life is risen a top of the languages, which gathers to God, and lets see before <hi>Babel</hi> or <hi>Babylon</hi> was, or <hi>Pilate</hi> either: and exalted <hi>Babel</hi> shall fall and become a habitation of Devils; but over all the life is risen, that gives to see to the beginning before the world was made, which brings to peace with God, which opens the words of Christ, the Prophets and Apostles, and gives to every one his particular satisfaction concerning the words of the Prophets of Christ, of the Apostles, in which life, peace with God is known, which judgeth all them that has the words, and be out of the life.</p>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:44856:16"/>
                     <p>ILE break into pieces, Ile make Nations like dirt, Ile tread them into Mire; Ile make reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, professions, teachings, time-servers, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers upon me with their lips and hearts afar off, sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fetting in the earth, pride, hypocrisie and deceitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of heart, gathered into a Religion thats vain, gatherings on heaps, gatherings of Multitudes, gatherings which they call Churches, fair shews, fair pretences, hypocritical teachings, selfe-ends, covetous practices, Ile make mire of them, Ile make morter, Ile make dirt of them, the wrath of the Lamb is risen upon all Apostates, who are gathered in the Apostacie, Apostatized from the Prophets life, the Apostles life, the life of the Lamb, the Lamb is risen, the scepter is gone out, the throne is set, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware every one what you profess, what foundations you are laying, you shall be shaken, not being in the possession, being out of the possession of the life of God, of the Prophets, of the Apostles of Christ. Ye diviners, ye dreamers, ye Notionists, in your curiosities in the air, Ile whirle you under hail-stones, viols, plagues, thunders, woes, judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are come amongst you, upon your heads all Nations that be out of the life of the Lamb, dread, quakings, fears, shall surprize hypocrites, amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the pure life of God is risen, that has been lost, from it ye have been Apostatized, without it have you been gathered, with it shall your gatherings be broken, scattered; From the life of my Apostles, of my Prophets have you been
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:44856:17"/>all scattered and Apostatized, and so true Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strie hath been lost, true Apostles life lost, true Prophets life lost, false Ministers got up, false Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles got up, false Prophets got up, and reigned in their stead: my sheeps cloathing you have had, wolves you have been, thorns and thistles your earth has brought forth, has laien like a wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse unplowed-up, amongst whom are so many names and horns, setting up your inventions, but inwardly ravined, so Apostatized, so the witnesse buried, whored, and then fornication; but the Rod is over you which must rule Nations, trump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets sounding and sounded, the just will rule, the Lamb will have the victory; woes, woes and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>series are out-going upon all the heads of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, the judgements are come upon the World, the day of glory is appearing, and hath appeared, the Throne and the Scepter that is everlasting is come and witnessed and set over the World, which shall answer that of God in every one, which eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one has ravined from, and all gatherings upon the earth from that, shall bee broken, and it shall answer the just in every one.</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:44856:17"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>